Guide to the Harold Edward Woodsum, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harold Edward Woodsum, Jr. papers
1984-1994
MS 1673
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.5
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, reports, meeting minutes, financial records, and other organization files that document Harold Edward Woodsum, Jr.'s terms on the board of directors of the National Audubon Society.
Woodsum, Harold Edward, 1931-
Conditions Governing Access
The material in boxes 15-18 is restricted until January 1, 2069 due to the requirements in the donor's deed of gift.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harold Edward Woodsum, Jr., 1994.
Arrangement
Arranged by topic
Scope and Contents
The papers document Harold Edward Woodsum, Jr.'s terms on the board of directors of the National Audubon Society (NAS). The collection consists of Woodsum's organizational files relating to board business and subject files relating to environmental issues. The files include correspondence to and from other board members, most notably Peter Berle, president of the National Audubon Society. Minutes of meetings, reports, financial records, and files relating to Woodsum's involvement in the annual Birdathon are also included.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Edward Woodsum, Jr. was born on August 13, 1931 in Portland, Maine, the son of Harold Edward Woodsum and Ethel York. He attended Yale University, earning a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1953 and a Bachelor of Laws degree in 1958. He was awarded an honorary Master of Arts degree from Yale in 1979. Woodsum later attended Westbrook College and earned a Doctor of Laws degree in 1991. He was co-founder and partner in the law firm of Drummond, Woodsum, Plimpton McMahon from 1965 to 1988. In 1988, Woodsum became the Director of Athletics of Yale University and remained in that position until 1994. He was elected into the Maine Sports Hall of Fame in 1992. Woodsum is a past trustee of both Yale University and Westbrook College.
A longtime supporter of environmental issues, Woodsum served in several organizations including the Maine Coast Heritage Trust. His thirteen year career in the National Audubon Society began with his election to the board of directors in 1981. He was elected treasurer in 1985 and served as chairman of the board from 1988 to 1993.
Birds; Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Woodsum, Harold Edward, 1931-; National Audubon Society
- Inventory, 1984-1994
  Scope and Contents
  The papers consist of materials created and accumulated by Woodsum while serving on the National Audubon Society (NAS) Board of Directors. The inventory is comprised of one alphabetical listing that incorporates organizational files and subject files. Files documenting the activities of the NAS Board of Directors include correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports, and financial records. Woodsum's correspondence to and from other board members comprises a significant portion of the papers. Correspondence between Woodsum and NAS President Peter Berle is listed under Berle. One folder of personal correspondence is listed at the end of the correspondence files. The files pertaining to Woodsum's participation in the annual Birdathon comprise another significant portion of the organizational files. The Birdathon files include correspondence, pledges, and sponsor lists. Subject files on environmental and conservation issues are interfiled with the organizational files and consist primarily of printed material.
  The original arrangement of the files was preserved where possible. Consequently, like materials, i.e. financial records, may be listed under separate headings. Cross-references have been created where appropriate
  - Acid rain, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adopt-a-pothole program, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ancient forests, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual dinner, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual meeting, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Annual reports, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Arctic refuge, 1988, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Audit information, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Audubon Adventures, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Audubon Cause, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Audubon [magazine]
    - General, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Membership business plan, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Beef industry, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Berle, Peter (President)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17-21)
    - Reports, 1988-1993 (Box 2, Folder 22-27)
  - Birdathon
    - 1989
      - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 28-30)
      - Guide for participants (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Pledges (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Sponsor lists (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1990
      - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Guide for participants (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Pledges (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Reception (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Sponsor lists (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - 1991
      - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Guide for participants (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - 1992
      - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Guides for participants (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Pledges (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Sponsor lists (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - 1993
      - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Guides for participants (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Pledges (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Sponsor lists (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Board of Directors
    - Bylaws and constitution, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Committee assignments, 1984-1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
      General note
      See also: box 5, folder 73
    - Correspondence, 1988-1994 (Box 4, Folder 52-54)
    - Lists [of board members], 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Meetings, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 56-57)
    - Nominating Committee
      - Nominees
        - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 58)
        - Lists [of nominees], 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Reports, 1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 60-61)
  - Budget
    - 1988-1989
      - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Reports (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Capital campaign, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Capital fund, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Chapter affairs, 1989-1993 (Box 5, Folder 68-70)
  - Clark estate, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Code of ethics, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Committee assignments, 1989-1993 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    See also: box 4, folder 51
  - Committees
    - Ad hoc on election process, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Chapters and regional activities, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Communications, 1990, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Education, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Evaluation, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Field operations, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - International, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Natural areas review, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Nominating, 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 82-83)
    - Planning
      - General, 1988-1993 (Box 6, Folder 84)
      - Five-year planning committee meeting, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Policy, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 86-87)
    - Wildlife report, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Contributions
    - Correspondence, 1988-1993 (Box 6, Folder 89-91)
    - Logs, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 92-96)
  - Corkscrew Water Treatment Plant, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Correspondence
    - A-B, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 98-99)
    - Berle, Peter
      General
      See also: box 2, folders 17-21
    - Bush, George, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - C, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 101-102)
    - Cadbury, B. Barton, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - D-G, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 104-107)
    - Grant, Robert, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - H-M, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 109-112)
    - Martin, Susan, 1988-1993, undated (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Miller, David, 1989-1993 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Nixa, Diane, 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - O, 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - O'Brien, Donal, 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - P, 1988-1992 (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Palmer, Chris, 1988-1990 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - R, 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Raisbeck, Elizabeth, 1988-1992 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Reed, Nathaniel, 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Reed, Scott, 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - S-W, 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 124-126)
    - Whitaker, John, 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Wightman, Barbara, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 128)
    - Yeager, Brooks, 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Personal, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 130)
  - Council symposium, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 131)
  - Country Life article, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - Development Department
    - Correspondence and reports, 1988-1993 (Box 9, Folder 133-135)
    - Garrison Conservatory district, 1990-1993 (Box 9, Folder 136)
      See also: box 10, folder 155
  - Ducks Unlimited, 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 137)
  - Dues sharing, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Earth Day, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Ecology camps [printed material], 1989-1992 (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Education, 1988-1991, undated (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - "Elephant Folios," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - Elmseed Project, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Endangered species, 1990-1993 (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - Energy, 1989-1991 (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - Everglades, 1991-1994 (Box 9, Folder 146-147)
  - Exxon Valdez, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 148)
  - Financial information
    - General, 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 149)
    - Presentations, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 150)
    - Statements and reports, 1988-1990 (Box 10, Folder 151-153)
  - Foundations, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - Garrison Conservatory district, 1989-1993 (Box 10, Folder 155)
    See also: box 9, folder 136
  - Gifts [real estate], 1989 (Box 10, Folder 156)
  - Grants, 1989-1993 (Box 10, Folder 157)
  - Grazing, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 158)
  - High priority campaign, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 159)
  - Hitachi Foundation, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 160)
  - Hog Island, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 161)
  - Investments [reports], 1989-1993 (Box 10, Folder 162)
  - James Bay, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 163)
  - Litigation, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 164)
  - Logo, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 165)
  - Long Island Sound
    - Correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 10, Folder 166)
    - Printed material, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 167-168)
  - Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 169)
  - Maine Coast Heritage Trust, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 170)
  - Maine Society, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 171)
  - Management consultants, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 172)
  - Marine resources, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 173)
  - Migratory bird program, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 174)
  - Minority hiring, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 175)
  - Mission statement, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 176)
  - New headquarters
    See also: box 5, folder 66
    - General, 1989-1993, undated (Box 11, Folder 177)
    - Capital campaign plan, 1990, undated (Box 11, Folder 178)
    - Clippings, 1990-1993 (Box 11, Folder 179)
    - Financing, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 180-181)
    - Printed material, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 182)
  - Newsletter, 1990-1991 (Box 12, Folder 183)
  - Niobrara hearing, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 184)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 185)
  - North American Waterfowl Management Plan, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 186)
  - Oak Hammock Marsh, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 187)
  - Oil industry, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 188)
  - Palladium Medal, 1990, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 189)
  - Personnel directories, 1986, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 190)
  - Pine Island, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 191)
  - Planned giving, undated (Box 12, Folder 192)
  - Platte River [Two Forks Dam opposition]
    See also: box 14, folder 221
    - General, 1988-1990 (Box 12, Folder 193)
    - Clippings, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 194)
    - Reports, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 195-196)
  - Population growth, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 197-198)
  - President's council, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 199)
  - Printed material, 1988-1991 (Box 13, Folder 200-203)
  - Reed, Scott [re: National Audubon Society convention], 1992 (Box 13, Folder 204)
  - Regional affairs, 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 205)
  - Reimbursement policy, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 206)
  - Research, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 207)
  - Retreat [staff], 1989 (Box 13, Folder 208)
  - Roper study, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 209)
  - San Pedro River, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 210)
  - Sanctuaries, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 211)
  - Science Department, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 212)
  - Science Institute, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 213)
  - Television and media programs
    - General, 1988-1993 (Box 14, Folder 214-215)
    - Printed material, 1988-1994 (Box 14, Folder 216)
  - Timber cutting, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 217)
  - Trips, 1990-1992 (Box 14, Folder 218-219)
  - Waste management, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 220)
  - Western water law, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 221)
    See also: box 12, folder 193
  - Wetlands
    - General, 1989-1992 (Box 14, Folder 222)
    - Printed material, 1989, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 223)
  - Wise Use movement, 1993, undated (Box 14, Folder 224)
- Restricted
  Conditions Governing Access
  The material in boxes 15-18 is restricted until January 1, 2069 due to the requirements in the donor's deed of gift.
  - Audubon [magazine], 1992-1993 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Berle, Peter [correspondence], 1992-1993 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors
    - General, 1991-1993 (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
    - Meeting minutes, 1990-1993 (Box 15, Folder 6-8)
    - Restructuring Task Force, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 9-10)
  - Case, Michael, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Christmas Bird [census], 1991-1992 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Cohen, Michael [correspondence], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Conflicts of interest, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Development Department [contribution logs], 1990-1991 (Box 16, Folder 15-17)
  - Evaluation Committee, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Finance Committee, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Financial information
    - General, 1992-1993 (Box 16, Folder 20-21)
    - Budget, 1990-1994 (Box 17, Folder 22-27)
    - Investments, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Kresge Foundation, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Litigation
    - Administration hearings, undated (Box 17, Folder 30-32)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Docket book updates, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 34-35)
  - Nominating Committee, 1989-1993 (Box 18, Folder 36-37)
  - O'Brien, Donal [correspondence], 1992-1994 (Box 18, Folder 38-42)
  - Property appraisal, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - Riley, William [correspondence], 1991-1993 (Box 18, Folder 44-45)
  - Working group, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 46-48)